The book of Genesis is the first book of the Bible.
ddfsfsgfg
Its story line divides into two main parts.
There are chapters 1-11 which tell the story of God and the whole world.
Then there are chapters 12-50 which zoom in and tell the story of God and just one man, Abraham,
and then his family.
These two parts are connected by a hinge story at the beginning of chapter 12.
This design gives us a clue as to how to understand the message of the book as a whole
and how it introduces the story of the whole Bible.
The book begins with God taking the disorder and the darkness described in the second sentence of the Bible.
Out of it, God brings order, beauty and goodness.
He makes a world where life can flourish.
God makes these creatures called humans or "adam," in Hebrew.
He makes them in his image, which has to do with their role and purpose in God's world.
So humans are made to be reflections of God's character out into the world.
They are appointed as God's representatives to rule his world on his behalf,
which, in context, means to harness all its potential, to care for it, and make it so that even more life can flourish.
God blesses the humans.
It is a key word in this book.
He gives them a garden, a place from which they begin starting to build this new world.
The key is that the humans have a choice about how they are going to go about building this world.
That is represented by the tree of the knowledge of good and evil.
Up until now, God has provided and defined what is good and what is not good.
But now God is giving humans the dignity and the freedom of a choice:
Are they going to trust God's definition of good and evil
or are they going to seize autonomy and define good and evil for themselves?
The stakes are really high.
To rebel against God is to embrace death because you are turning away from the giver of life himself.
This is represented by the Tree of Life.
In chapter 3, a mysterious figure, a snake, enters into the story.
The snake is given no introduction, other than saying it is a creature that God made.
It becomes clear that it is a creature in rebellion against God.
It wants to lead the humans into rebellion and their death.
The snake tells a different story about the tree and the choice.
It says that seizing the knowledge of good and evil are not going to bring death,
that it is actually the way to life and becoming like God themselves.
The irony of this is tragic because we know the humans are already like God.
They were made to reflect God's image.
But instead of trusting God, the humans seize autonomy.
They take the knowledge of good and evil for themselves.
In an instant, the whole story spirals out of control.
The first casualty is human relationships.
The man and the woman suddenly realize how vulnerable they are.
They cannot even trust each other.
So, they make clothes and they hide their bodies from one another.
The second casualty is that intimacy between God and the humans is lost.
So they go, run, and hide from God.
When God finds them, they start this game of blame-shifting about who rebelled first.
Right here, this story stops.
There is a series of short poems where God declares to the snake and then to the humans
the tragic consequences of their actions.
God first tells the snake that despite its apparent victory, it is destined for defeat, to eat dust.
God promises that one day a seed, or a descendant, will come from the woman, who is going to deliver a lethal strike to the snake’s head.
This sounds like great news, but this victory is going to come with a cost
because the snake, too, will deliver a lethal strike to the descendant's heal as it is being crushed.
It is a very mysterious promise of this wounded victor.
But in the flow of the story so far, you see that this is an act of God's grace.
The humans have just rebelled.
What does God do?
He promises to rescue them.
But this doesn't erase the consequences of the humans' decision.
So God informs them that now every aspect of their life together--at home and out in the field--
is going to be fraught with grief and pain because of the rebellion, all leading to their death.
From here, the story then spirals downward.
Chapters 3-11 trace the widening ripple effect of the rebellion and of human relationships fracturing at every level.
There is the story of two brothers, Cain and Abel.
Cain is so jealous of his brother that he wants to murder him.
God warns him not to give in to the temptation but he does anyway.
He murders him in the field.
So Cain then goes on to build a city where violence and oppression reign.
This is all epitomized in this story of Lamech.
He is the first man in the Bible to have more than one wife.
He accumulates them like property.
He goes on to sing a short song about how he is more violent and vengeful than Cain ever was.
After this, we get an odd story about the "sons of God" which could refer to evil, angelic beings,
or it could refer to ancient kings who claimed that they descended from the gods.
Like Lamech, they acquired as many wives as they wanted and they produced the Nephilim, these great warriors of old.
Whichever view is right, the point is that humans are building kingdoms that fill God's world with violence and even more corruption.
In response, we are told that God is broken with grief.
Humanity is ruining his good world and they are ruining each other.
So out of a passion to protect the goodness of his world, he washes it clean of humanity's evil with a great flood.
But he protects one blameless human, Noah, and his family.
He commissions him as a new Adam.
He repeats the divine blessing and commissions him to go out into the world.
So our hopes are really high.
But then Noah fails too, also in a garden.
He goes and plants a vineyard and gets very drunk.
Then one of his sons, Ham, does something shameful to his father in the tent.
Here we have our new "Adam," naked and ashamed, just like the first.
The downward spiral begins again.
It all leads to the foundation of the city of Babylon.
The people of ancient Mesopotamia come together around a new technology they have: the brick.
They can make cities and towers bigger and faster than anybody has ever done before.
They want to build a new kind of tower that will reach up to the gods.
They will make a great name for themselves.
It is an image of human rebellion and arrogance.
It is the garden rebellion now writ large.
So God humbles their pride and scatters them.
Now, this is a diverse group of stories but you can see they are all exploring the same basic point:
God keeps giving humans the chance to do the right thing with his world
and humans keep ruining it.
These stories are making a claim that we live in a good world that we have turned bad--
that we have all chosen to define good and evil for ourselves.
So we all contribute to this world of broken relationships, leading to conflict, violence, and ultimately death.
But there is hope.
God promised that one day a descendant would come--
the wounded victor who will defeat evil at its source.
So despite humanity's evil, God is determined to bless and rescue his world.
The big question is, of course, "What is God going to do?"
The next story, the hinge, offers the answer.
But, for now, that is what Genesis 1-11 is all about.